Guide to the George T. Clark Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George T. Clark papers
1862-1935
SC0292
Clark, George T., 1862-1940.
2 Linear feet
These papers relate primarily to Clark's research on the life of Leland Stanford and include correspondence, 1924-1935, historical documents, 1862-1893, clippings, photographs, and two notebooks, 1928-1930,for his comprehensive biography of Senator Leland Stanford, published by the Stanford University Press in 1931. Correspondents include George C. Clark, Dumas Malone, Stuart Daggert, Timothy Hopkins, and V. S. McClatchy; there is also a long letter by C. C. Crippen concerning his work as a horse trainer on the Palo Alto Stock Farm and his knowledge of Leland Stanford. Historical documents include copies of correspondence between Stanford and J. D. B. Stillman, 1882-1883, concerning Eadweard Muybridge and Stillman's book, THE HORSE IN MOTION. Other items include Clark's memorial address on J. L. Gillis; and a "want list" for the Stanford University Library, 1920.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Douglas Clark, 1983-1985.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Clark was Stanford University Librarian, 1907-1928 (emeritus 1928 until his death in 1940) and co-founder and first president of the California Library Association.
Description of the Collection
These papers relate primarily to Clark's research on the life of Leland Stanford and include correspondence, 1924-1935, historical documents, 1862-1893, clippings, photographs, and two notebooks, 1928-1930,for his comprehensive biography of Senator Leland Stanford, published by the Stanford University Press in 1931. Correspondents include George C. Clark, Dumas Malone, Stuart Daggert, Timothy Hopkins, and V. S. McClatchy; there is also a long letter by C. C. Crippen concerning his work as a horse trainer on the Palo Alto Stock Farm and his knowledge of Leland Stanford. Historical documents include copies of correspondence between Stanford and J. D. B. Stillman, 1882-1883, concerning Eadweard Muybridge and Stillman's book, THE HORSE IN MOTION. Other items include Clark's memorial address on J. L. Gillis; and a "want list" for the Stanford University Library, 1920.
Access Terms
Clark, George C.; Clark, George T., 1862-1940.; Crippen, C. C.; Daggert, Stuart.; Gillis, J. L. (James Louis), 1857-1917.; Hopkins, Timothy, 1859-1937.; Malone, Dumas, 1892-1986; McClatchy, V. S. (Valentine Stuart), 1857-1938.; Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904; Palo Alto Stock Farm (Stanford, Calif.); Stanford University. Libraries.; Stanford, Leland, 1824-1893.; Stillman, J.D.B. (Jacob Davis Babcock), 1819-1888.; California --History --1849-; Notebooks.; Photoprints.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Stanford-Huntington episode 1890: clippings, 1888-1890 (bd. vol.)
    - Also includes biographical sketches and obituaries for C. F. Crocker, C. P. Huntington, John Corning, E. C. Fellows, and others (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Leland Stanford material (bd. vol.)
    - Copies of clippings, 1857-1875, 1902; and copies of documents from the Bancroft Library - reminiscences of Stanford by H. C. Nash, William H. Mills, and Henry Vrooman; Stanford's comments on Bancroft's manuscript; and comments from Charles Crocker (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Leland Stanford's Addresses and Public Communications (bd. vol.)
    - Clippings, copies of clippings, typescript copies, and some original pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notebook, 1927-1929; notes on Stanford's life from interviews and research (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notebook, 1929 and undated; notes on Stanford's life by years and by subjects (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Biographical sketch of Jane L. Stanford for the Dictionary of American Biography, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Booklet on the new Stanford Library, with section by Clark, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chapter notes (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Clark, George T., article on, 1928 (Stanford Illustrated Review) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1887, and 1917-1935:
    - George C. Clark on Muybridge research (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - C. C. Crippen on Stanford and horses, with newspaper article (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Timothy Hopkins on piece of Stanford ephemera (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - R. G. Kraemer re Port Washington research question (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - M. P. Lilienthal with photostat of L. Stanford note (1882) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Dumas Malone re JLS biography for DAB (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Grant L. Stanford re location of Stanford home in Watervliet, NY (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Talbot H. Wallis (1887) re Clark's appointment as Deputy State Librarian (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Ray L. Wilbur with note by Frank Shay regarding last letter of Stanford (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence regarding DAB biography of Leland Stanford, 1932-1933:
    - Stuart Daggert, Timothy Hopkins, Dumas Malone, George T. Clark (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with V. S. McClatchy, 1924, 1929, re James McClatchy (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Gillis, J. L., manuscript of Clark's memorial address, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Grant, J. D., The Stanfords, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Motion picture tablet on campus, 1929 - program, article, typescript of J. D. Grant's remarks (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Notes on political history (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Notes, miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Photographs and illustrations used in Clark's book (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Photograph of library staff, 1914 (Frederick E. Brasch, T. L. Smith, Philip D. B. Perham, Lena Rose Neth, Thomas L. Dyer, Charles V. Park, Lillian Hollmann, and Albert Harold Morosco) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Politics - contemporary clippings, 1862-1892 [some copied] (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Railroads - contemporary clippings, 1869-1892 [some copied] (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Railroad documents: Stewart vs. Huntington, 1886; stock and bond statement for Central Pacific Railroad Company, 1874 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Stanford - biographical/ historical clippings, 1889-1928 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Stanford-Bancroft clash, manuscript and typescript article by Clark (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Stanford-Stillman letters [copies], 1882-1883, re Muybridge (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Stanford University Library want list, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - University - clippings, 1887-1893 (Box 3, Folder 22)
General note
Unpublished guide available.